好吧，我想我们可以开始了欢迎回来这是第15场演讲
all right I guess we can get started
welcome back it's the 15th lecture of
最后一次我们离开的浓缩课程，我们正在谈论试图
the condensed matter course when last we
left off we were talking about trying to
近似求解固体中电子的薛定inger方程，并且
approximately solve the Schrodinger
equation for electrons in solids and the
我们正在讨论使用的方法是近乎自由电子模型
method we were talking about using was
the nearly free electron model nearly
自由电子的基本概念是，我们要写我们的哈密顿量
free electrons the general idea of being
that we're gonna write our Hamiltonian
就像一些裸露的规则无相互作用的电子平面波
as some bare just regular non
interacting electron plane wave
哈密​​顿量加上一些势，因此在平面波K中的本征态为
Hamiltonian plus some potential so the
eigenstates of this in a plane wave K is
H bar平方K平方超过2m只是常规电子哈密顿量，
H bar squared K squared over 2m just
your regular electron Hamiltonian but
那么在这里我们有一些周期性的潜力
then here we have some periodic
potential which we're going to
最终认为自己是弱者，因此这个名字几乎具有自由潜力和想法
eventually consider to be weak hence the
name nearly free potential and the idea
我们从散射理论中得出的结论是，一些K之间的矩阵元素
that we took from scattering theory is
that the matrix element between some K
如果K减去K素数不是一个整数，则该周期性势的K素数必须为0。
and K prime from this periodic potential
has to be 0 if K minus K prime is not an
倒数晶格的元素，如果K素数减去K，我们将其称为V sub G
element of the reciprocal lattice and
we'll call it V sub G if K prime minus K
互易晶格中是否存在元素，因此我们将
is there an element in reciprocal
lattice so then we treated the the
势v为弱摄动和二阶摄动理论
potential v as a weak perturbation and
in second-order perturbation Theory
二阶燃烧我们发现平面波K的能量开始为
second-order burn we found that the
energy of the plane wave K starts out as
平面波的裸能量K加V sub 0的零阶傅里叶模式
the bare energy of the plane wave K plus
V sub 0 the zeroth Fourier mode of the
势，这只是所有平面波能量的整体转移
potential it's just an overall shift of
all of the plane wave energies that's
无趣的人有时只是将它们放在一起，因为它只是一个常数
uninteresting people sometimes just drop
it all together cuz it's just a constant
但是有趣的是所有倒数晶格向量V的总和
but the interesting piece is the sum
over all reciprocal lattice vectors V
子G乘以K减去能量而不是K加G的平方，所以这是我们的
sub G squared over energy of K minus
energy not of K plus G so this is our
二阶摄动理论表达和必须要做的事情
second order perturbation Theory
expression and the thing that one has to
担心的是分母可以为零或接近零，并且
worry about is that the denominator can
be either zero or close to zero and that
当我们使K绝对K等于
happens when so this diverges
when we have K absolute K being equal to
绝对K加G使得K n ng k加G的能量相同，即
absolute K plus G so that the energy of
K n ng k plus G are the same and that is
等于k和k加G在易边界Braun上的相同条件
equal to the same condition as k and k
plus G being on on easy boundary Braun's
自己的边界，所以在这种情况下，我们的二阶摄动会出现问题
own boundary so in that case we have a
problem our second order perturbation
理论由于这种退化以及我们应该做的事情而无法工作
theory doesn't work because of this
degeneracy and what we're supposed to do
我们应该使用生成扰动理论来简并赫兹吗
is we're supposed to use the generate
perturbation theory degenerate Hertz
抵制所有关于堕落这个词开玩笑的理论可能有
theory resisting all urges to make jokes
about the word degenerate probably have
在简并扰动的一般规则之前被做了数百次
been made hundreds of times before the
general rules of degenerate perturbation
理论上是，您应该采取导致您麻烦的状态
theory are that you should take the
states that are causing you trouble the
使您与众不同的州将那些与众不同
states that are giving you the
divergence separate those out from all
系统中的其他州，并以此来困扰汉密尔顿
the other states in the system and just
to agonize the hamiltonian with this
在那些有问题的国家的空间内，所以对我们来说，我们的国家
within the space of those problematic
states so for us ours the states that
导致我们麻烦我们的州的K和K加G对于某些特定的G，所以我们会
are causing us trouble our state's K and
K plus G for some particular G so we'll
写我们的试验波函数，实际上可能会更通用一些
write our trial wave function actually
maybe will be a little bit more general
并假设K和K加G假设它们在棕色区域边界附近
and assume assume K and K plus G assume
these are near a brown zone boundary
mihrab容易划分边界，因此它可能不会出现实际差异，而可能只是一个
mihrab easy boundary so it may not be in
an actual divergence it can just be an
耳朵发散仍然很严重，足以使我们不信任二阶
ear divergence it's still bad enough to
cause us to not trust our second-order
摄动理论不再存在，要求我们使用简并摄动理论
perturbation Theory anymore and require
us to use degenerate perturbation theory
即使不是分母，您也知道分母不是零
even though it's not a you know it's not
a zero in the denominator so something
分母接近零的一般方案是写一个试验波
close to zero in the denominator the
general scheme is to write a trial wave
功能，这将是一些有问题的猫，所以K和K加
function which is going to be some some
of the problematic cats so K and K plus
G可能会取这两个值的线性和，并且我们通常会尝试
G will may take some linear sum of these
two and in the usual way we will try to
找到这两只猫的最佳线性组合
find the best linear combination of
these two cats
为了获得这个空间内的最低能量状态，所以我们做了一个
in order to get our lowest energy state
within this space so we've done this a
在做某事之前几次是写下哈密顿量
couple times before the way one does
that is you write down a Hamiltonian an
在m H和M Phi上的有效哈密顿方程总和等于e Phi，并且
effective Hamiltonian equation sum over
m H and M Phi M equals e Phi and this
从解决紧密绑定模型时所做的事情中应该看起来很熟悉
should look familiar from what we did
when we solved the tight binding model
对于共价键的共价键，此hmm是一个二乘二矩阵
for the covalent for the covalent bond
here this hmm is a two by two matrix
从k和k加G中选择N和M，这就是您的操作方式
where N and M are chosen from k and k
plus G this is how you how you do the
一般微扰理论，您只是将状态空间限制为
general perturbation Theory you just
restrict the space of states to the
在第二级引起麻烦的退化国家的空间
space of degenerate States who are
causing trouble in the second-order
摄动理论没事，所以我们现在要做的唯一一件事就是
perturbation theory all right so the
only thing we need to do now in order to
遵循这个规定是我们需要写出矩阵元素H
follow this prescription is we need to
write out the matrix elements H so for
例如，我们有KHK是四个矩阵元素之一，我们可以这样写
example we have K H K that's one of the
four matrix elements we can write that
作为KH零K加KVK，因为我们的哈密顿量由H零组成
as K H naught K plus K V K since our
Hamiltonian is made up of the H naught
部分和V部分这部分很容易这只是一个K结
part and the V part this part is easy
this is just a knot of K and this part
V是零，只是整体恒定的能量位移，这下标是
is V naught just the overall constant
energy shift this together subscript is
0，因为K减去K素数是0，类似地，k加ghk加G等于e naught
0 because K minus K prime is 0 similarly
k plus g h k plus G is equal to e naught
的k加G加V之和再次无效
of k plus G Plus V naught again the more
interesting term is the term the off
2 x 2矩阵k加上GH的对角项，所以让我们写出
diagonal terms of the 2 by 2 matrix k
plus G H okay so let's write out the the
这部分我们有第一个k加GH没关系，第二个是K
pieces of this we have first k plus G H
naught okay and the second piece is K
再加上GV好吧，第一部分很容易，因为这将是H否K
plus G V ok well the first part this is
easy because this would be H naught K is
H的本征态，所以我们可以拉出一个
an eigenstate of H naught so we can just
pull out an
不是子K并得到K加G好的，但这是零，因为它们是两个正交的
not sub K and get K plus G okay but this
is zero because these are two orthogonal
平面波，所以它是零，第一项是0第二项是我们定义的
plane waves so it's zero the first term
is 0 the second term is we've defined
由于它是V sub G，所以我们被允许通过k从k分散到k加G
that as being V sub G so we're allowed
to scatter from k to k plus G via the
分散电势G并向上移动到顶部oops我将其滚动到顶部
scattering potential G and up way up at
the top oops I scrolled it off the top
[音乐]是的，它在D sub G的顶部
[Music]
yeah there it is on the top the D sub G
的K减去K的素数是G的元素，所以我们称这个东西为V sub G，所以我们
of K minus K prime is an element of G so
we call this thing V sub G so so what we
现在也是如此，这件事将是整体，这将是V sub
have now is also so this thing is going
to be overall this is going to be V sub
G，我们可以做另一个最后一个矩阵元素HK加G
G and we can do the other last matrix
element H K plus G which using the same
自变量是负G或负G星
argument is the sub minus G or the sub G
star
这是它的合作伙伴的复杂共轭，所以现在我们有了
it's a complex conjugate of its of its
partner up here so now we have our
哈密​​顿方程我们的2 x 2矩阵，我们可以记下e结为K + V结
Hamiltonian our 2 by 2 matrix we can
write down which is e knot of K + V knot
我们从这里开始有V sub G，从这里开始有V sub G，然后没有N + K + G + V
we have V sub G here start here V sub G
down here and e naught K + G + V not so
太好了，每个人对此或多或少都感到满意，只是过快了
far so good everyone happy with this
more or less just go by too quickly
是的，幸福，好，好的，所以对于家庭作业和问题集4我
yeah happy ok good all right so for
homework and what's problem set 4 I
认为您通常会在地面附近的K上实际解决此问题
think you're going to actually solve
this in general for a K near the ground
区域边界使代数更加复杂，但是
zone boundary which makes the algebra a
little bit more complicated but what
我们要在这里做我们要简化我们的代数
we're gonna do here is we're gonna
simplify our algebra a little bit and
假设K在棕色区域边界上正确假设K和K加G我们在BZ上
assume K is right on the brown zone
boundary assume K and K plus G our on BZ
BZ边界上的边界只是使代数更容易一点，所以
boundary on BZ boundary just to make the
algebra a little bit easier so that
表示II不等于K等于e不等于k加G相同的能量
means that II not of K equals e not of k
plus G the same energy so right on the
简并点，在这种情况下，这是一个非常简单的矩阵
degeneres point in which case this is a
very simple matrix has to
沿对角线然后复共轭的元素相同
elements which are the same along the
diagonal and then complex conjugate
非对角线上的矩阵元素和能量是II而不是K
matrices elements on the off diagonal
and the energies are then II not of K
加V而不是加或减绝对VG，这就是我们的答案，那么这是什么
plus V not plus or minus absolute V G
and that's our answer so what is this
这是什么意思，让我们也许在这里画出来，所以我们有
what does this mean
let's maybe draw it here so we have
这是K这是能量E，在添加扰动之前，我们有一个很好的
here's K here's energy E and before we
add the perturbation we have a nice
抛物线我们通常画它，所以这是通常的抛物线
parabola we have the usual draw it this
so this is the usual parabola which is a
K的点数等于H bar平方K平方超过2m，所以这是自由电子
nod of K equals H bar squared K squared
over 2m so that's the free electron
抛物线，那么我们可以放下它具有一定布朗区的周期性势
parabola then we can put down the
periodic potential it has some Bron zone
边界，所以我在PI上有一些晶格常数柏林区域边界
boundary for this so I had some lattice
constant a Berlin zone boundaries at PI
在负PI上，除了在a和负2 PI处有更多的*区域边界
over a minus PI over a except more bran
zone boundaries at minus 2 PI over a and
2 PI在此处，因此此处此处的*区域边界减去PI在
2 PI over a here so here at this point
there's bran zone boundary minus PI over
a和PI在a上，您可以通过此倒易的晶格矢量G散布在它们之间
a and PI over a you can scatter between
them by this reciprocal lattice vector G
等于PI超过a可以使您从负PI减去2超过PI的秒数
equals to PI over a can get you from
minus PI over a 2 PI over a so in second
阶次扰动理论如果您分析了这一点，您会发现
order perturbation Theory you would
discover that if you if you analyze this
指向此处或指向此处，您将在第二阶出现分歧
point here or this point here you would
get divergence in second order
扰动理论，我们将不得不使用简并扰动理论
perturbation Theory and we would have to
use degenerate perturbation theory in
为了弄清楚这些点发生了什么，我们得出的是
order to figure out what happens to
these points and what we just derived is
事实上，他们在能量上的分裂以及它看起来的方式是
it in fact they split in energy and the
way it's going to look is that this is
会向下移动，然后会向上移动一点，因此实际上
going to shift down and then this will
shift up a little bit so that in fact
您会在左侧的东西之间拉开一点缝隙
you open up a little gap between the
things coming from the left of the
东西从右边进来，它的大小是-绝对VG在这里和相同
things coming in from the right and it's
size is - absolute VG here and the same
事情在这边发生，像这样扩大了大小的差距-绝对
thing happens over on this side like
this opens up a gap of size - absolute
VG和同样的事情会在这里发生，您可以从Braun的身上散开
VG and the same thing would happen up
here where you can scatter from Braun's
自己的边界布劳恩自己的边界G等于a上的四个PI，这里是一个间隙
own boundaries Braun's own boundary by G
equals four PI over a and here a gap
会在这里的青铜器边界处打开，而间隙会在
would open up at the bronze own boundary
here and the gap would open up at the
这里是青铜自己的边界，所以自从我画得很糟以来
bronze own boundary here okay so since
I've drawn that fairly badly I was
为此做准备，我有一张幻灯片，所以这是同一张照片的扩展区域
prepared for this and I have a slide so
here's the same picture an extended zone
方案这是从抛物线开始的，漂亮的自由电子
scheme this is the starts with the bare
parabola the the nice free electron
抛物线，然后当您添加周期性电势时，
parabola and then when you add the
periodic potential the major effect of
周期性电势接近其打开的男爵区边界
the periodic potential is near the
barone zone boundary where it opens up
这个间隙，您会注意到青铜自身边界内的状态
this gap you notice that the states
inside the bronze own boundary get
降低一点能量，如果
pushed down in energy by a little bit
and they get pushed down more if they're
更接近青铜器自身的边界，因为当您接近青铜器时
closer to the bronze own boundary
because as you're close to the bronze
如果您以二阶微扰理论来思考的话，那就是自己的边界
own boundary if you think in second
order perturbation theory that's where
分歧越来越严重，实际上并没有
the divergence is getting worse and
worse and worse it doesn't actually
分歧，但随着您的不断变化，扰动变得越来越重要
diverge but still the perturbation is
becoming more and more important as you
更加接近青铜器自身的边界-间隙使事物被压低
get closer to the bronze own boundaries
- the gap opens things get pushed down
当您接近青铜器自己的边界时，还有更多，然后如果您就在外面
more as you get close to the bronze own
boundary and then if you're just outside
青铜器本身的边界物体被推高，而您打开这小块
the bronze own boundary things get
pushed up and you open up this little
在柏林区域边界的差距现在这里完全相同
gap at the Berlin zone boundary same
thing over here now we're perfectly
有权在缩小区域方案中查看相同的内容
entitled to view the same thing in
reduced zone scheme where we take this
频谱，我们将其移了两个pi，所以就在这里
piece of the spectrum and we shift it
over by two pi over a so it's over here
然后，我们利用这一频谱范围，将两个PI移到一个
and we take this piece of this spectrum
we shifted over by two PI over a in the
另一个方向，直到它在这里，我们在第一个视图中查看所有内容
other direction until it's over here and
we view everything within the first
布里渊区，但现在我们在第一个青铜区中有两个乐队
Brillouin zone but now we have two bands
within the first bronze zone so we have
最低的频段，我们有一个较高的频段，这看起来有点像我们
a lowest band and we have a higher band
and this looks a little bit like what we
在几周前研究紧束缚模型时发现
found when we studied the tight binding
model in a couple weeks back we handle
因为当我们每个晶胞有两个轨道时，在两个值处有两个波段
for when we had two orbitals per unit
cell there were two bands at two values
在每个可能的K值处有两个本征态
of two eigenstates at each possible
value of K which is what we have here
并且结构看起来或多或少相似，我们有一个低频段，一个高频段，然后一个
and the structure looks more or less
similar we have a low band a high then a
棕色区域边界处的缝隙开口，但是我们实际上是从
gap opening at the brown zone boundary
however we're really coming at this from
当我们进行紧密绑定模型时，这是一个非常互补的方向，我们从
a very complementary direction when we
did tight binding model we started by
取一堆轨道，然后我们将它们弱耦合在一起，并允许
taking a bunch of orbitals and then we
weakly coupled them together and allow
电子从一个轨道到另一个轨道
the electrons to
from one orbital to the next to the next
在这里，我们做的是相反的，我们从平面波开始，然后我们对其进行了微弱的扰动。
here we did the opposite we started with
a plane wave and we weakly perturbed it
具有周期性的电势，但是无论用哪种方式观察，都可以得到相同的物理场
with a periodic potential but either way
you look at it you get the same physics
如果您从柏林的边界区域中分离出不同的带隙
of separate bands gaps at the Berlin
zone boundary if you look at it from the
几乎免费的电子模型，虽然实际上这张图片可以在这张图片中看到
nearly free electron model though really
this picture you can see in this picture
这实际上是一个自由电子抛物线，在
it's it's actually just a free electron
parabola with small perturbations at at
柏林地区的边界，所以这种抛物线在
the Berlin zone boundaries so this
parabola is sort of continued in the
第二个乐队，所以这片抛物线星反射回来，
second band so this this piece of the
parabola star reflected back and
继续第二个乐队，因为差距，他们不太感动
continuing the second band they don't
quite touch because of the the gap
打开，但实际上给出了该带在底部附近的曲率
opening up but the curvature of this
band near the bottom is actually given
由自由电子质量引起底部弯曲的事物
by the free electron mass the thing that
causes the curvature at the bottom of
你的抛物线取决于自由电子质量而不是其他任何东西
your parabola that's dependent on the
free electron mass not on anything else
所以我们真的应该查看乐队的这个底部，看起来像一个
so we really should view this this
bottom of the band which looks like a
抛物线基本上就是自由电子，所以这个问题是
parabola is just being essentially free
electrons okay so a question that's
在这一点上相当重要的是，也许我将其放在这里是为什么差距
fairly important at this point is maybe
I'll put it over here is why the gap why
差距介意差距为何差距还可以，所以才能理解为什么
the gap mind the gap why the gap okay so
in order to understand why it is that
这种差距正在以另一种语言在柏林地区边界开放
this gap is opening up at the Berlin
zone boundary in a different language
举个例子很有用，这样可以检查一个特定的潜力
it's useful to to give an example so
examine a particular potential I'll
选择X的V，我们将在一维中执行此操作实际上这是一个
choose V of X and we're gonna do this in
one dimension actually this is one
维度我还应该提到，这不是一个维度
dimension also I should have mentioned
that this isn't one dimension this is
更重要的是，这是一个更通用的方程式
more this is a more general equation
which all hold in any dimension we're
我们也要在一维上做这个例子，所以X的V我们选择它为2
gonna do this example in one dimension
also so V of X we'll choose it to be two
V旋转余弦2pi超过X倍，这是一个很好的周期性电势
V twiddle cosine 2pi over a times X
that's a nice periodic potential maybe
我什至会得出每个人可能都知道它看起来什么样的周期性潜力
I'll even draw that periodic potential
everyone probably knows what it looks
喜欢，但我还是会画它，好吧，这是我们的X是X也许我们会在这里放一个
like but I'll draw it anyway so okay
here's our X is X maybe we'll put a here
减去这里，余弦势看起来像这样，看起来像这样
minus a out here and a cosine potential
looks like this and looks like this
因此，这是X的V，晶格常数是a，周期是a和
so this is V of X and the lattice
constant is a the periodicity is a and
之所以选择这种特殊的简单余弦势，是因为它
the reason I've chosen this particular
simple cosine potential is because it
具有很好的傅立叶模式v等于V的sub 2pi等于v的负sub 2pi
has nice Fourier modes v sub 2pi over a
equals V sub minus 2pi over a equals V
旋转，所有其他所有V sub G等于0，所以它只有两个
twiddle and all other all other V sub G
are equal to 0 so it only has two
非零的傅立叶模式，它们都由V旋转梗死给定
Fourier modes which are nonzero and
they're both given by V twiddle alright
所以现在让我们考虑一下这将要做的事
so now let's think about what this is
going to do what this can do is it can
V sub G的散射仅对G而言是2 pi，因此在此图片中表示
scatter by V sub G only for G is 2 pi
over a so in this picture it means it
可以从这个点散布到这个点4到G这是两个点
can scatter from this point to this
point 4 by G these are the two points in
退化摄动理论，他们可以彼此混合，这就是重点
degenerative perturbation theory they
can mix with each other that's point
K等于a的负PI，K等于a的正PI，所以散射
that K equals minus PI over a and K
equals plus PI over a so the scattering
我们要担心的是k等于a上的PI减去PI，而2 K等于PI上的PI
we have to worry about is from k equals
minus PI over a and 2 K equals plus PI
被这个电位来回散布，因此它可以向后散射
over a being scattered back and forth by
this potential so it can scatter back
在青铜器本身上的两个波矢量之间来回
and forth between those two wave vectors
which are right on the bronze own
边界，所以在现实空间中，如果我考虑这些的XK表示
boundary so in in real space if I think
about X K representations of these of
这些猫是X上的I PI，e上是减去I PI的e
these cats these things are either the I
PI over a X and e to the minus I PI over
X，如果我们将这个哈密顿量对角化
a X and I'll use that notation if we
then diagonalize this Hamiltonian in
那就是在这个空间中，我们将得到两个特征值或
that and that's in this space what we'll
get is we'll get our two eigenvalues or
我们这边的两个本征函数将是e VI pi over ax加e到负I
two eigenfunctions our side plus will be
e VI pi over a x plus e to the minus I
X上的PI及其能量E Plus在零加V旋转条件下为e sub pi，
PI over a X and it's energy E Plus is e
sub pi over a naught plus V twiddle and
另一个本征符号减号是e到I PI，而X减号e是到负I
the other eigenstate sign minus is e to
the I PI over a X minus e to the minus I
PI超过X且其能量为e-PI高于零
PI over a X
and it's energy e - is e naught PI over
负V旋转，所以这些平面的这些线性组合之一
a minus V twiddle so one of these linear
combinations of these of these plane
波浪的能量被推高其中之一被能量的推低
waves is getting pushed up in energy one
of them is getting pushed down in energy
由V旋转，所以我们又有了这两个平面波
by V twiddle so again we have these two
plane waves one going left one going
正确的是，他们被这种散射的潜力混合在一起
right they're getting mixed together by
the by this by this scattering potential
通过这种周期性的潜能和两个本征态之一
by this periodic potential and one of
the two eigenstates this has been pushed
增强能量其中一个被降低了能量为什么我们要
up an energy one of them has been pushed
down in energy why is that well let's
看看我们是否能弄清楚，让我们将边+平方，然后我们得到
see if we can figure that out
let's take side + square it so we get
概率密度，所以这是密度，问题概率密度
the probability density so this is the
density the problem probability density
概率密度sy +平方，建议的部分全部-余弦平方
prob density sy + squared which is
proposed portion all - cosine squared of
PI在ax + sy-平方上与PI over的正弦平方成比例
PI over ax + sy - squared will be
proportional to sine squared of PI over
一个X，让我们在同一图上画出它们，让我们看一下sy +看起来像这样
a X and let's plot those on this same
figure so let's see sy + looks like this
它的余弦平方为SI +平方，然后为sy-看起来像这叹气-平方
it's cosine squared of SI + squared and
then sy - looks like this sigh - squared
看起来像这样，所以它们的幅度误差概率密度在
looks like that so they have their
amplitude err probability density is in
沿着位置空间的不同地方
different places along the in the
positional space there different places
沿轴，因此侧面加平方的角度使我
along the axis and because of this the
side plus squared sees I'm putting that
用引号引起来的X大多是正VV，因此您可以看到sy +的优势所在
in quotes sees mostly positive V V of X
so you see where where sy + is great
X的V为正且很大的地方
where it's very large
that's where V of X is positive and
我们在里面+小是X的V为负的地方，这意味着边加E
we're inside + is small is where V of X
is negative so that means side plus E
Plus被推高了，能量被推高了，因为它主要经历了
Plus is pushed up in energy is pushed up
because it's experiencing mostly the
正电位，而正弦减去平方
positive potential whereas in comparison
sine minus squared
大部分搜索X的负VV，因为sy-大，而X的V恰好是
sieze mostly negative V V of X because
sy- is large where V of X happens to be
负数，所以它被降低了u负数的能量被降低了，所以让我们
negative and so it's pushed down u minus
is pushed down down in energy so let's
仔细考虑一下，这是怎么回事
think about this a little bit more
carefully so what's going on is we have
这个空间有向左波和向右波，这是
this space which has a left going wave
and a right going wave that's the the
简并摄动理论的空间
space of the degenerate perturbation
theory and you know with the variational
原则上我们应该做的是将它们放在一起
principle what we're supposed to do is
we're supposed to put them together in a
你会知道如何获得基态的方法
way that will you know to get the ground
state we're supposed to put them
一起以最小化总能量和最小化方式
together in a way that will minimize the
total energy and the way you minimize
获得基态的总能量是将它们放在一起
the total energy to get the ground state
is you put them together such that you
得到一个符号-因为符号-在X的V为负且
get a sign - because sign - has its
maximum where V of X is negative and
降低了能量，因此在其中将其降低了
that pushes down its energy therefore
it's in it pushes it down as much as
因此，这可能是我可以陈述的基态，反之，sy +
possible therefore it's the ground state
I can state and conversely sy+
通过投入尽可能多地提高其能量
has pushed up its energy as much as
possible as high as possible by putting
势为正的密度，那么为什么
its density where the potential is
positive so is that clear what why
一切都很好，所以你读过检查员的报告吗
that's going on alright good so do you
ever read the examiner reports people
阅读考官的报告，您从来没有注意到它真的很讨厌，我认为这是
read the examiner reports you've never
notice that really nasty I think it's an
书面要求审查员报告必须真的很讨厌
unwritten requirement the examiner
reports have to be really nasty I've
从来没有参加过考试委员会，但是有一天我会来的，我会
never been on the examination committee
yet one day my time will come and I'll
可能会在平板电脑上某处读到该规则的未成文规则
probably read the rule the unwritten
rule somewhere on some tablet that says
你一定很讨厌，所以这几乎引起了一个问题
you must be nasty okay so there was a
question that came up about this nearly
自由电子模型大约是在四年前出现的，它真的引发了很多
free electron model came up about four
years ago and it really threw a lot of
人，所以我要经历那里所涉及的物理学
people so I'm gonna go through the
physics of what was involved in there
这并不比我们做的复杂得多，但是
which isn't too much more complicated
than what we did but but it's something
你知道很多人都觉得很意外，所以我要
that you know a lot of people found
rather unexpected so I'm going to
或多或少地解释该问题发生了什么，所以当您遇到
explain more or less what what was going
on in that problem so when you run into
有一天它不会打扰您，所以我们将考虑一个正方形
it someday it won't trouble you so we're
going to consider a square
二维晶格，我正在画一个倒数空间，这是倒数
two-dimensional lattice and I'm drawing
reciprocal space this is a reciprocal
格子2D这个正方形2D格子和
lattice so Square 2d
this Square 2d lattice and the
正方形格子的倒数空间也是正方形，所以我要画
reciprocal space of a square lattice is
also square so I'm going to draw the
棕熊拥有，所以这里的K等于零，第一个铜牌拥有
Bruins own so this is K equals zero here
in the center and the first bronze own
这里是这个广场，拐角处的这个点是PI超过8 pi超过8 ok
is this square here and this point here
in the corner is PI over 8 pi over 8 ok
现在，这个问题要求您要做的第一件事就是找出当
now the first thing this question asked
you to do is find out what happens when
您添加了周期性电势，在青铜板上的某个点会发生什么
you add a periodic potential what
happens to a point here on the bronze
自己确定边界，所以基本上这就是我们刚才所做的
own boundary ok so that's basically
exactly what we just did
由于周期性的电位，它可以与该点混合
that point there due to the periodic
potential it can mix in with this point
在这里，这两个点被倒易的晶格矢量隔开，这是一个
over here these two points are separated
by a reciprocal lattice vector this is a
倒数晶格矢量2 pi超过a的2 pi，因此这两个可以通过
reciprocal lattice vector 2 pi over 2 pi
over a so these two can mix together via
散射它们具有相同的能量，因为它们与k的距离相同
scattering they have the same energy
because they're the same distance from k
等于0，它们具有与k相同的振幅，所以此条件保持EK
equals 0 they have the same amplitude of
their k so so this condition holds EK
等于ek加G，所以它们混合在一起，这是我们完全相同的计算
equals ek plus G so they mix together
and it's exactly the same calculation we
只是做到了，只是您知道这实际上是一个二维模型，但我们只是
just did it's just you know it's really
a two dimensional model but we're just
考虑到切穿的二维，将会有一个缺口
considering this cut through two
dimensions there will be a gap opening
在这一点上，在柏林区域边界上
up at the Berlin zone boundary at this
point at this point so that much is
简单还是应该简单我希望它就像我们两次做的一样
simple or should be simple I hope it's
exactly like what we did in two
一维和一维，但现在在二维中，
dimensions and in one dimension but now
in two dimensions the thing that was
如果您在此处考虑这一点，将会发生复杂的情况
complicated is what happens if you
consider this point up here in the
拐角处，所以这称为两点一，所以现在我们要做的是
corner so it's called this point two
point one so now what we have to do is
我们必须问他们在哪里做的分歧在哪里
we have to ask where do they do where do
the divergences come in second order
扰动理论很好，这一点人们可以被倒易的晶格散射
perturbation theory well this point one
can scatter by a reciprocal lattice
向量到第二点，但它也可以通过倒数晶格向量进行散布
vector to this point two but it can also
scatter by a reciprocal lattice vector
至第三点，这也是至此的倒数晶格向量
to this point three and this is also a
reciprocal lattice vector to this point
四个，实际上是分叉柜分散了两个三四个可以分散到
four and in fact forking cabinets
scatter two three four can scatter to
两个可以分散到三个，它们都可以通过倒数彼此分散
two can scatter to three they can all
scatter to each other by reciprocal
格向量那些在k空间中的向量都是倒数格向量
lattice vectors those vectors in k space
are all reciprocal lattice vectors and
他们都被允许彼此混合，并且在拥有相同能量之前
they're all allowed to mix to each other
and they all have the same energy before
您添加扰动，所以当您进行简并扰动理论时
you add the perturbation so when you do
your degenerate perturbation theory
您会发现一堆这些东西，所有这些分母
you'll find a bunch of these things the
bunch of these denominators that are all
零，如果您正在考虑这一点
zero
okay if you're considering this point
散射到这里分母为零散射到这里
scattering to here there'll be a
denominator zero scattering here
零散在这里，所以你要处理的方法是你必须写你的
scattering here all zero so the way you
handle this is you have to write your
试用波函数，它包括试验，它包括所有这些波向量，所以我
trial wavefunction it includes trial it
includes all of these wave vectors so I
想要1加披披2 K 2 + 5 3 K 3 + 5 4 K，因为所有这些事情
want a 1 plus Phi 2 K 2 + 5 3 K 3 + 5 4
K for all of these things have to be
包含在您的试验波函数中，然后您的哈密顿量就是4乘4
included in your trial wavefunction and
then your Hamiltonian is then a 4 by 4
矩阵，其中包括您如何来回分散的所有可能性
matrix which includes all possibilities
of how you scatter back and forth
在所有这四个点之间都可以，所以这就是
between all those four points okay so
that was what was what was asked on the
在考试中，即使不是
in the in the exam and a lot of people
got thrown by it even though it's not
真的要复杂得多，好吧，好吧，让我们开始吧
really that much more complicated okay
good happy with that all right let's do
我们在这里做一个真实的例子，所以在3D真实的例子中，我们有很多东西
it let's do a real example here so in 3d
in real example real life we have things
就像FCC格子一样，就像我们几天前讨论的那样
like FCC lattices this is as we
discussed a couple days ago this is the
FCC晶格的青铜区，伽玛点是K中等于0的点
bronze zone of the FCC lattice the gamma
point is a point at K equals zero in the
x点的中间是此正方形中间的柏林区域边界
middle the x point is at the Berlin zone
boundary in the middle of this square
面对此处，L点位于KX方向，位于柏林区域边界
face here and the K X direction the L
point is in the Berlin zone boundary in
例如，该六边形表面的中间以及我们要使用的材料
the middle of this hexagonal face for
example and the material we're going to
考虑一下实际上是材料碳化硅
think about is the material silicon
carbide silicon carbide it's actually
这是另一种重要的工业材料，它具有这种结构
it's another important industrial
material it has this structure here it's
FCC有一个基础，因此黄色是硅的，蓝色是
FCC with a basis so the yellows are
silicon's and the and the Blues are
碳可以在0 0 0处取，碳可以在1/4 1/4 1/4处取
carbon the silicon can be taken at 0 0 0
and the carbon at 1/4 1/4 1/4 we've seen
这是之前的这种结构Vinc混合结构硫化锌镓
this structure before this is this Vinc
blend structure zinc sulfide gallium
砷化物具有相同的结构，因此碳化物具有这种结构
arsenide takes the same structure
so looking carbide takes this structure
这是非常常见的结构，现在可以了，所以在这里让我们看看是否可以
it's very common structure ok now all
right so here let's see if we can we can
了解这张照片如何显示所有本征的复杂照片
understand how this picture this
complicated picture of all the eigen
电子的状态可以来自几乎自由的电子模型，所以让我们
States for electrons can come out of
nearly free electron models so let's
低头看最低的能量这里的最低能量
look down at the lowest energy the
lowest energy here and we have the gamma
点在K等于0是，电缆0的另一个名称
point that's at K equals 0 yeah
another name for cable zero and as you
在柏林地区朝X点走出去，你会看到
go out in the Berlin zone towards the
point X you see this thing that looks
有点像抛物线，如果你备份，那很糟糕
kind of like parabola and if you back up
that's oops back back back back back
这里看起来有点像抛物线，这就是
here so it looks kind of like this
parabola here and that's exactly what
你在这里看到这是从K出来的自由电子抛物线
you're seeing here this is the free
electron parabola coming out from K
等于零，当您到达青铜自己的边界时，会有一个间隙
equals zero and when you get to the
bronze own boundary there's a gap
打开，这是抛物线的后半部分在他的背上
opening up and this is the second half
of the parabola going up around his back
回来不在这里，所以这里是抛物线的后半部分
back back not there here it is so here's
the second half of the parabola up here
就像抛物线的后半部分在这里一样，您可以进入
just like the second half of the
parabola is here and you could go off in
另一个方向，所以从伽玛到L点再一次
another direction so going from gamma
out to the L point again you have a
抛物线，这是L方向的较大缝隙，这是第二个
parabola and this is slightly bigger gap
in the L direction and here's the second
抛物线的一半在这里还可以，所以基本上是自由电子模型，如果
half of the parabola here okay so it's
basically free electron model and if you
在波段底部向下测量曲率，您的伽玛等于零，
measure the curvature down at the bottom
of the band your gamma equals zero you
基本上得到自由电子的质量，这不完全是
get basically the mass of the free
electron it's not exactly the mass of
自由电子，但它非常接近自由电子的质量
the free electron but it's it's pretty
close to the mass of the free electron
在30％或20％之内，所以它确实告诉您
within 30 percent or 20 percent or
something so so it really tells you that
底部附近发生了什么，基本上是自由平面波物理学
what's going on near the bottom there is
basically free plane wave physics just
X点散射您的散射电位使它稍微受到干扰
perturbed slightly by the scattering
potential that the X point scatters you
跨越Brauns自己并打开了这个缺口
across the Brauns own and opens up this
gap is that clear so far all right so
大约六年前，我们的考试题目非常讨厌
we're on the subject of really nasty
exam questions about six years ago there
这是一个考试问题，没有一个学生能正确完成，
was an exam question about this that not
a single student got right and the
考官在这方面让您知道了疯子，而您对这可怕的事情感到愤慨
examiner went you know in berserk on
that and you've ranted about the awful
学生等等，但是嗯，但是你知道这就是你所需要的
students and so forth but uh but you
know it's just you know that's required
他们要做的，但实际上问题实际上是非常困难的
of them to do but it actually the
question was actually quite difficult
而且我认为这是我要向您解释问题的根源
and and I think it was I'm gonna explain
to you what the question was about it's
如果您以前没看过的话，很难
something that if you hadn't seen it
before it would be very very hard to
弄清楚，但我想期望是你应该
figure it out but I guess the
expectation was you were supposed to be
教过它，我认为没有人教过，所以现在我要教它
taught it and I don't think anyone
taught it so now I'm going to teach it
所以如果它出现了，你们都会知道的，所以问题就在于
so if it comes up you'll all know it so
the the question was about it's
比较像这样的东西和像硅的东西，所以这是
comparing something like this to
something like silicon so this is
硅看起来完全像碳化硅，唯一的区别是
silicon here it looks exactly like
silicon carbide the only difference is
而不是四分之一一季度一季度的碳
instead of carbon at one quarter one
quarter one quarter you
将这些碳与另一个硅放在一起，所以全都是硅硅零零
place those carbons with another silicon
so it's all silicon silicon zero zero
每季度四分之一的硅含量为零，我们已经看到了这一点
zero in silicon at one quarter one
quarter one quarter we've seen this
之前的结构这也是与钻石相同的结构
structure before too
this is the same structure as diamond
硅和金刚石结构等同于相同的晶体结构
silicon and diamond structure are
equivalent same same crystal structure
实际上，如果您在这里查看K的两个两个能量本征能谱
and actually if you look at the two two
energy eigen energy spectra here of K
从底部到顶部，它们实际上是硅和硅
across the bottom and energy up top
they're actually silicon and silicon
碳化物，它们看起来几乎不错，我不会说完全相同，但非常相似
carbide they look almost well I wouldn't
say identical but extremely similar a
一个中的许多功能都存在于另一个中，所以您知道
lot of the features in one are there in
the other as well you know so for
例如，在这里您具有相同的抛物线，但您会注意到只有一种
example here you have the same parabola
but you'll notice there's one one sort
令人震惊的区别是，青铜器自身的边界处没有缝隙
of shocking difference here that there's
no gap at at the bronze own boundary
在这个X点，在这里X点，抛物线聚在一起，它们
here at this X point the X points here
the parabolas come together and they
他们不，他们根本不分裂，所以应该推论的是
they don't they don't split at all and
so what one is supposed to deduce is in
X点根本没有积雪散布的事实
fact that there's no snow back
scattering at the X point at all for
硅中的某些原因您不会在X点处散射
some reason in silicon you do not get
scattering at the X point okay
所以现在我们要设法弄清楚为什么如此首先
so it's so now we're gonna try to figure
out why that is so first of all for the
巧克力棒，X点的散射从一侧的X点开始
chocolate bar the scattering at the X
point goes from an X point on one side
拥有的青铜器的另一侧拥有什么是米勒
of the bronze own to the opposite side
of the bronze own what are the Miller
与该倒易的晶格矢量相关的索引
indices associated with that reciprocal
lattice vector what not no one no this
真的很好零零一个是一个很好的猜测，但是不正确
is really good zero zero one is a very
good guess but it's not right does
任何人都想要另一个猜测，不，不，所以零零一个是正确的方向
anyone want another guess no no no and
so zero zero one is the right direction
或者实际上我想它在X方向上，或者如果您愿意的话，它在一个零零
or actually I guess it's in in in the X
direction or one zero zero if you prefer
如果您在X方向上进行操作，那将是指向
if you're doing in the X direction it
would be if that would point be pointing
在正确的方向上，因为X在KX方向上，而负X将是
in the right direction because X is in
the K X direction and minus X would be
在相反的KX方向上，所以在1 0 0方向上
in the opposite KX direction so be in
the 1 0 0 direction that you're
散射或0 0 1（如果您采用其他方法），那么这是正确的
scattering or the 0 0 1 if you're going
the other way so that's the right
方向，但不是1 0 0，而不是1 0 0，是因为1 0 0
direction but it's not 1 0 0 and the
reason it's not 1 0 0 is because 1 0 0
不是FCC晶格的倒数晶格矢量，您会记得回到
is not a reciprocal lattice vector for
FCC lattice and you'll remember back to
这幅画在这里，他们记得那个
this picture here they remember that
ones
如果您定义零，则是简单立方晶格的倒数晶格
zero is a reciprocal lattice for the
simple cubic lattice if you define the
一零零米勒指数的飞机，你会在这里得到这些飞机，但FCC
planes by the one zero zero Miller index
you get these planes here but the FCC
格在中间有一些额外的格点，所以一个零零是
lattice has some additional lattice
points in the middle so one zero zero is
没有得到所有的最后点，因此它不是倒数晶格
does not get all the last points
therefore it is not a reciprocal lattice
FCC晶格的矢量2零零是最小的倒易晶格
vector for the FCC lattice two zero zero
is the smallest reciprocal lattice
向量在那个方向上，所以这里是从X 2减去X的散射，我什至
vector in that direction so here is
scattering from X 2 minus X I'll even
写下来，对于硅阱，X 2减去X散射为2 0 0
write that down so X 2 minus X
scattering is 2 0 0 for silicon well
实际上对于任何CC晶格X 2减去X都是2 0 0好的，所以我们得到了
actually for anything CC lattice X 2
minus X is 2 0 0 ok so we've gotten that
到目前为止，问题是为什么为什么在2 0 0处没有散射
far now the question is why is it that
we don't get any scattering at 2 0 0
Miller指数有没有人想过我还剩下这些呢？
Miller index does anyone want to guess
of that I have one more of these left
好吧，我听不见谁是Matt的，是的，
well is it
I can't hear who the the Matt's yeah and
虽然它们都是硅，是的，所以那不是对你没有帮助
while they both silicon's so yeah so so
that doesn't that doesn't do it for you
其他任何FCC晶格都是具有基础的FCC晶格，所以我不会
any other it is FCC lattice is an FCC
lattice with a basis so I'm not gonna
为此给你，但它已经接近那个，所以也许我会给你
give you give it to you for that but
it's close to that so maybe I'd give you
它的一半，但我不知道该怎么做，所以它不是纯粹的，不只是
a half of this but I don't know how to
do it so so it's not pure it's not just
FCC晶格，这就是必须跟踪
an FCC lattice and that's the point that
it's you have to keep track of the
在基础中找出是否有散射，所以让我们考虑
lattice in the basis to find out if
there's there scattering so let's think
回到我的意思是FCC晶格，但如果硅是
back to I mean is an FCC lattice but it
allows the silicon if the silicon is a
基于八次的点阵加法，所以如果我们考虑我们学到的东西
lattice plus of eight times a basis so
if we think about what we learned about
来自x射线散射的散射记住s是s晶格乘以s
scattering from from x-ray scattering
remember that s is s lattice times s
基本权，S是给您散射权的幅度，如果我们
basis right and the S is what gives you
the amplitude of scattering right if we
方屁股，您得到的散射幅度适用于X射线，它
square ass you get the amplitude of
scattering this worked for x-rays and it
也会对电子起作用，因此强制选择规则的晶格
will work for electrons as well so s
lattice that enforces selection rules
执行选择规则
enforce selection rules
并且0-0实际上满足了FCC晶格的选择规则
and to 0-0 actually satisfies the
selection rule for an FCC lattice all
对于FCC来说，偶数都是奇数，两个零零都是偶数，所以我们可以接受
even are all odd for FCC two zero zero
is all even so we're okay with that so
那不会消失，但是让我们看一下基础
that's not gonna that's not gonna vanish
but let's look at s basis that's basis
您会记得是e的单位格中的Adams alpha与F sub alpha的总和。
you'll recall is sum over Adams alpha in
unit cell of e to the F sub alpha the
形状因子e到i gr alpha，如果我们对硅这样做，它将得到F
form factor e to the i gr alpha and if
we do this for silicon will get F
硅，然后在零零零处将为1，然后我们将
silicon and then it'll be one for the
point at zero zero zero and then we'll
将e设为2 pi，然后将散射的米勒指数设为零零
get e to the 2 pi and then the Miller
indices of the scattering to zero zero
乘以晶格点的位置四分之一，四分之一，四分之一
times the position of the lattice point
one quarter one quarter one quarter like
从我们的X射线散射历险中看起来很熟悉吗
that does this look familiar from our
x-ray scattering adventures yeah ok so
您会注意到这里的东西实际上是负1，所以s为零
you'll notice that this thing here is
actually minus 1 so s basis is zero so
在硅上没有2 0 0方向的反向散射，因为有
there's no back scattering in silicon in
the 2 0 0 direction because there's you
知道我会给我的，我还是会给你的，因为哎呀，因为我不想
know I'll give it I'll give this to you
anyway because oops because I don't want
自己保留它，因为我会吃它，而且我的体重一直在增加，所以还可以
to keep it myself because I'll eat it
and I've been gaining weight so ok so so
这样您就不会在2 0 0中返回散射，但是通过
或0，因为这是告诉您的是
the or 0 because there's it's a what
this is telling you is that there's
两种硅的散射之间的确切破坏性干涉
exact destructive interference between
the scattering of the two silicon's in
它们都会散布的晶胞，但随后您将遭受破坏
the unit cell they'll both scatter but
then you get exact destructive
受它们的干扰，因此实际上，在
天，这个物理原理实际上是您知道它在X射线中弯曲
day and this this physics is actually
it's you know it curves for x-rays in
硅在2 0 0方向上没有硅的X射线散射
silicon there's no scattering of x-rays
for silicon in the 2 0 0 direction it
电子的曲线没有电子X点的反向散射
curves for electrons there's no back
scattering of the X point for electrons
在硅中，声子也会发生。让我们看一下这是
in silicon it also occurs for phonons
let's see here's the phonon spectrum for
硅，看起来很像钻石的声子光谱，但不是
silicon this looks a whole lot like the
phonon spectrum for diamond but not
巧合的是，因为它是相同的晶体结构，所以这里是硅
coincidentally because it's the same
crystal structure so here's the silicon
来自它的声子，所以我们去了
phonons
from it has so we went we had this uh
以前每个K向量有六个声子，因为每个K矢量
previously there's six phonons at every
K vector because there are two atoms per
基本单位单元，每个单元都向三个方向移动，所以有六个
primitive unit cell and each one moves
in three directions so there's six
光子一二三四五六六
photons one two three four five six and
A three of them are acoustic coming down
现在，您会注意到，如果您在此处的X点处查看此点
here now you'll notice if you look at
this point here at the X point in this
图片碳化硅有一个缝隙在此图片中没有缝隙
picture silicon carbide a gap has opened
up in this picture a gap has not opened
甚至来自声子波
up and it's coming from essentially the
same physics even with phonon waves that
在两个零零方向上没有反向散射，因此您不会
in the two zero zero direction there's
not back scattering therefore you don't
有一个缝隙的开口，而在碳化硅II中则没有
have an opening of a gap whereas in
silicon carbide II you don't have
完美的取消，因为这个词将有F硅这个词会
perfect cancellation because this term
would have F silicon this term would
碳彼此不相等的碳，所以你仍然会回来
have F carbon those don't equal each
other so you would still have back
分散，您在Barone自己的边界上会留出空隙，好吧，我
scattering and you have a gap opening up
at the Barone's own boundary okay so I
意识到这是一个您知道有点复杂的问题，但是
realized this is this is a you know a
little bit complicated but it was on an
考试，希望您知道如果再次参加考试，人们将能够
exam and hopefully you know if it comes
up on an exam again people will be able
使它正确，但我确实承认，如果您之前从未见过
to get it right but but I do admit that
if you've never seen that before
这很难弄清楚，所以好吧
it's something that's pretty hard to
figure out so all right so having
基本讨论了我们需要了解的几乎所有免费内容
basically discussed everything that we
need to know about the nearly free
电子模型，我们现在可以继续讨论带理论带
electron model we can now move on to
talking about generally band theory band
电子的结构带理论，所以这些复杂的图片在这里
structure band theory of electrons so
these complicated pictures here they're
碳化硅再次具有其所有本征的复杂图景
silicon carbide again with it's
complicated picture of all its eigen
停留在每一个K中，所以让我们开始谈论UH
stays in every every K so let's um we
started talking about about the UH
理论，当我们谈论紧密绑定模型时，也许我们来画一幅画
theory when we talked about the tight
binding model maybe let's draw a picture
一些乐队在这里，所以这里是能量
of some bands like over here so here is
energy
这是这个方向上的K，所以我会自己画青铜
here's K in this direction so I'll draw
the bronze own there's a bronze own from
减去两个PI上的PI，然后您可能会有一些像
minus PI over a two PI over a and then
you might have some band that look like
然后是一个更高的波段，看起来像这样，也许还有更高的波段
this and then a higher band that looks
like this and maybe some higher bands up
现在在这里，还有我们提到的一些事情
here as well
now some things that we mentioned when
我们讨论的紧密绑定模型是，如果您有一个填充带
we talked about the tight binding model
is that if you have a filled band filled
带和间隙加上间隙，您得到的绝缘子等于绝缘子重复
band and a gap plus gap you have an
insulator equals insulator repeating
这是因为它非常重要，所以如果我们填充乐队，我们会说
this because it's fairly important so if
we fill a band we fill say
这个带和下一个带的间隙，我们有一个绝缘体，原因是
this band and a gap to the next band we
have an insulator and the reason this is
绝缘子是因为基本上没有放置位置的自由
an insulator is because there's
basically no freedom of where to put
您的电子，除非您克服了下一个能带之间的间隙
your electrons unless you overcome the
gap to the next to the next band which
上升到下一个频段可能需要很多能量
could be a lot of a lot of energy
required to get up to the next band you
根本无法重新排列电子，它们无法吸收任何无法吸收的热量
can't rearrange the electrons at all
they can't absorb any heat they can't
进行更改，他们无法更改其动量，因为所有动量状态
run change they can't change their
momentum because all the momentum states
已经充满了，所以基本上基本上是惰性的，所以我写
are already filled so it's basically
just completely inert so I'll write that
向下是惰性的，如果您有两个频段又被完全填充
down it's inert and if you have two
bands that are completely filled again
您将在下一个频段使用一个应用程序，它也将成为绝缘体
you'll have an app to the next band it
will also be an insulator a little bit
Naumann clay Chur有用的是填充最高的乐队
of Naumann clay Chur which is useful is
the highest filled band highest filled
带通常被称为价带价带，所以在这里这将是一个
band is usually called the valence band
valence band so here this would be a
价带和最低空下最低空人称为
valence band and the lowest empty down
lowest empty man is known as the
导带对于摇滚乐队来说也是个好名字
conduction band which would also be a
really good name for a rock group so if
任何人都可以组成一个摇滚乐队，我建议一个命名的乐队
anyone makes a rock group I'm suggesting
a named conduction band okay
所以另一个重要的陈述是，绝缘体的间隙很小
so another important statement that
insulator with small gap with a small
间隙间隙被称为半导体，此处的间隙小于4
gap gap is known as a semi conductor and
small here is sort of less than about 4
电子伏特等于它被称为半导体
electron volts equals this is known as a
semi conductor
而这种命名的原因是，如果间隙足够小
and the reason for this nomenclature is
that if the gap is sufficiently small
那么在零温度下这仍然是一个非常好的绝缘体，但是在
then at zero temperature this would
still be a really good insulator but at
如果间隙小于约四个电子伏特，则为室温300开尔文
room temperature 300 Kelvin if the gap
is less than about four electron volts
那么一些电子仍然可以从填充的电子中获得热激发
then a few electrons will still be able
to get thermally excited from the filled
带进入空带，所以您将有几个电子自由运行
band into the empty band so you'll have
a couple electrons running around free
只是热占据了导带，它们将携带一定量的
just thermally occupying the conduction
band and they will carry some amount of
当前你会得到一些电子在这里跑来跑去
current that you'll you'll get a couple
of electrons running around up here and
这将使他们能够携带少量的电流
that will allow them to carry some small
amount of current some small amount of
导电性，所以它是一种半导体，导电性很差，但是
conductivity so it's a semi conductor
conduct sort of semi conducts poorly but
它的行为类似，可以吸收少量热量，但不会吸收大量热量
it conducts similarly it can absorb a
small amounts of heat but not a lot of
因为只有极少数的电子可以重新排列，所以这很有意义
heat because only a very few electrons
can be rearranged okay that makes sense
是的，所以实际上这张碳化硅图片
yeah okay so actually so this picture of
silicon carbide silicon carbide these
这里所有的谱带都充满了费米能量，或者化学势位于
bands here all filled the Fermi energy
or the chemical potential lies in the
间隙的中间，所以您可以说它是绝缘体或半导体，
middle of this gap so you would say that
it's an insulator or semiconductor and
如果您看一下这点之间的能量差，最低
if you sort of look at the difference in
energy between this point the lowest
导带的点，这里是最高带
point of the conduction band and this
point here which is the highest band
指向价带，它小于40 V，所以我们说
point to the valence band
it's a little less than 40 V so we say
碳化硅是一种半导体，好吧，我们还提到了其他一些东西
silicon carbide is a semiconductor okay
there's something else that we mentioned
当我们谈论紧密结合模型时，电子在计数
when we talked about tight binding model
is that counting electrons is counting
电子和状态对于弄清楚是否存在
electrons and States is rather important
to figuring out if you have a filled
波段或不波段，如果您的系统中有n个单位单元，则您有n个K状态K
band or not if you have n unit cells in
your system then you have n K States K
状态，但此时您有两个自旋状态，每K自旋状态就可以了，
States but then you have times two spin
States spin States per K okay means that
两个n电子将填充一个能带，将填充能带，得到2 n个电子
two n electrons will fill a band will
fill band and this to get 2 n electrons
每个晶胞需要两个电子
you need two electrons per unit cell
因此，您期望如果您有任何偶数个偶数个电子
so that you expect that if you have any
any even number even number of electrons
每晶胞本身的电子数，您会期望
per unit cell number of electrons per
unit cell itself you would expect that
您可以填充可以填充整数的带数整数带的数，所以让我们
you can fill can fill integer number of
bands integer number of bands so let's
以碳化硅为例，所以碳化硅
take the case of silicon carbide for
example so silicon carbide silicon
碳化物，所以碳化硅的化合价都是四价
carbide so silicon carbide both valence
four so silicon and carbon both valence
形成两个化合价等于四，这意味着我们应该算
form both valence for valence equals
four which means we should count for
如果每个电子都可以，那么为什么我要
electrons for each of them okay if you
wanted to count all of the so why am I
只计四个而不是全部电子，原因是
only counting four instead of all of
their electrons the reason is because
这只是我们实际上通常只计算最外层外壳中的电子
it's only we really generally only count
the electrons in the farthest out shell
因为任何更远的贝壳都是完全惰性的，它们只是称重而已
because any of the farther in shells are
completely inert they just weigh buried
能量要低得多，但是如果您想算一下，它们的弹壳就是
had much much lower energies but if you
wanted to count they're filled shells as
好吧，您会发现它们充满了弹壳，所以也是如此
well you would discover that they're
filled shells are all even as well so so
对于硅和碳，我们仍然会有偶数个电子
we would still have an even number of
electrons both for silicon and carbon so
图中的原始晶胞这里的乳脂晶胞有四个
the primitive unit cell here cream unit
cell in this picture it has four
电子四对八电子共一硅原子一碳
electrons four sorry eight electrons
total total one silicon atom one carbon
每个载有四个电子的原子，所以我们应该填充四个能带I
atom each carrying four electrons so we
should fill four bands four bands I
想想我在一周左右或更早之前就钻石问了同样的问题
think I asked the same question about
diamond about a week ago or more and in
事实上，如果您计算的是费米能量以下的波段数
fact if you count the number of bands
here which are below the Fermi energy
一共有四一二三四，他们都满了，我们确实有
there are four of them one two three
four and they're all filled we do have
这里有些混乱，如果您在这里数，它看起来像
this little bit of a confusion here that
if you count here it would look like
只有三个，但是如果仔细看，您会注意到这两个向量
there's only three but if you look more
carefully you'll notice this vectors two
这里的乐队聚集在一起并具有相同的能量，所以这个实际上是
bands here which come together and have
the same energy so this one is actually
刚好有两个乐队
two bands it just happened to have the
same
在这里他们有不同的能量，所以你可以算出实际上有四个
here they have different energies so you
can count that there's actually four of
他们，所以在碳化硅中所有这四个带被填充，所有这些
them so in silicon carbide all these
four bands are filled and all these
这里的乐队是空的好好是是好好好现在在
bands up here are empty good good yes
yes okay good all right now in in
相比之下，我们的金属有部分填充带，部分填充带几乎
contrast we have metals have part filled
bands part filled bands which is almost
永远都是正确的，我可能会写得大多是真实的
always true
mostly I may write mostly true either
今天或下一次，我们将讨论为什么大多数情况下都是正确的。
today or next time we'll discuss about
why it's only mostly true mostly true
对于奇数个电子，为奇数个，每晶胞为
for odd for odd number of electrons odd
number electrons per unit cell for
例如，如果我们有这样的照片，那么这是青铜器，这是乐队
example if we had a picture like this so
here's the bronze own here's a band
这是一个带，假设每个单位电池有一个电子
here's a band suppose we have one
electron per unit cell if that would be
足以填满最低频段的一半，所以我们充满了一颗心
enough to half fill the lowest band and
so we have a heart filled down this is
每个单位电池部分填充一个电子，这里我们将其称为
one electron per unit cell part filled
band here and we would call this thing a
金属，因为带子只有部分填充，所以我们可以降低能量
metal because since the band is only
part filled we can make low energy
通过从填充点到未填充点带走电子来激发
excitations by taking electron from the
filled point to the unfilled point
任意低的能量我们也可以改变这些充满的动力
arbitrarily low energy we can also
change the momentum of these filled
通过仅从此处获取一些电子并移动它们来实现状态
States by just taking some of the
electrons from over here and moving them
以非常低的能源成本在这里转移整个
over here at very low energy costs are
just slightly shifting the entire the
整个图片稍微向右移动以填充更多状态
entire picture slightly shifting it to
the right to fill a couple more states
在这里，这里的州少一些，因为您正在更改
over here and a few less fewer States
over here and since you're changing the
在这种情况下，您实际上是在增加电流，因此通过改变
momentum you're actually adding current
in that case so by changing momentum of
所有这些电子实际上已经改变了总电流
all these electrons you've actually
changed the total electrical current in
该系统，因此由于它可以承载电流，我们称其为金属
that system and so since it can carry
current we call it a metal
但是金属也可能发生金属也以偶数发生
however metals can also occur metals
also occur also occur with even number
每个单元电池的电子数量是偶数
with even number of electrons per unit
cell also something I mentioned a couple
几周前，当我们讨论紧密绑定模型时，发生的方式是
weeks ago when we discussed tight
binding model the way that happens is
如果您的最低乐队看起来像这样，这是您的青铜乐队
here's your bronze own if you have a
lowest band that looks kind of like this
然后你有一个更高的频段像这样下降
and then you have a higher band that
dips down like this
你和你曾经说过，每个晶胞有两个电子就足够了
you and you had say two electrons per
unit cell that would be just enough
电子填充一个带，但你我的意思是你可以选择填充一个
electrons to fill one band but you I
mean you could choose to fill this
整个频段，如果您想要整个最低频段，那将是
entire band if you wanted to this entire
lowest band but that would be
与部分填充两个频段相比，在能量上不利
energetically unfavorable compared to
partially filling both of the bands so
相反，最好是部分填充并部分填充而不是
instead it's better to partially fill
this and partially fill this instead of
在较低的频带中填充这些较高的能量状态确实有意义
filling these higher energy states in in
this lower band does that make sense yes
是的，好的，所以在这种情况下，频段重叠，如果频段重叠
yes okay good so so in this case it
bands overlap I'll write this if bands
重叠重叠，看起来有点像，当我画画时您知道不自然
overlap overlap and it looks on it looks
a little you know unnatural when I draw
这样，但是如果您回头看一下碳化硅带
it this way but if you would look back
to the to the silicon carbide band
在这里的结构，您当然可以想象到您的脑袋
structure here you could certainly
imagine your head that this minimum just
进一步下降一点，这个最大值上升了一点
dipped down a little bit further and
this maximum came up just a little bit
更进一步，如果那是真的，那么这个最小值就低于这个费米
further and if that were true so that
this minimum went below this Fermi
能量，它超过了费米能量，然后是一些电子
energy and this went above the Fermi
energy then some of the electrons that
以前在这个乐队中被填补，然后进入这个乐队
was previously in this band that was
filled would then go into this band
它是空的，可以降低能量，所以一件事，我们真的
which was empty to lower the energy okay
so one thing that we that's really
跟踪频段之间的差距有多重要，因此如果
important to keep track of is how big
are the gaps between bands so if the
乐队之间的差距真的很大，那么您将不会有这个
gaps between the bands are really huge
then you're not going to have this
曾经发生过这种情况，您知道波段之间的距离足够远
situation ever occur you know that the
bands are sufficiently far apart then
他们不会重叠，所以我们的差距有多大我们的差距有多大
they're not going to overlap so how big
our gaps how big our gaps big our gaps
乐队之间的差距
between bands gaps between bands
问题很好，我们用不同的方式来描述我们如何理解乐队
question well we had different ways of
describing how we understand the band
结构描述它的一种方式是从紧密结合中的紧密结合
structure one way of describing it was
from tight binding in the tight binding
我们称它为一个带每个带每个带来自一个原子轨道的图片
picture we called it a band each band
each band comes from an atomic orbital
来自能量为e的原子轨道原子轨道
is from an atomic orbital
atomicorbital with energy of energy e
能量称为子I，带宽是从跳变到弹出
with energy it's called a sub I and the
bandwidth is from hopping from popping a
PT，因此如果原始原子轨道彼此之间的间隔很好
PT so if the original atomic orbitals
are very well spaced apart from each
其他，跳动很小，那么乐队没有机会重叠
other and the hopping is small then the
bands don't have a chance to overlap
因为最初彼此之间的距离很远，所以跳动是
because initially start very far apart
from each other and the hopping is what
将频带从单一能量扩展到频带，因此如果跳跃是
spreads the band out from a single
energy into a band so if the hopping is
小，能量间隔大，那么谱带不会重叠，所以
small and the energy spacing is large
then the bands won't overlap so that's
一种理解它的方式，这是理解它为何的一种自然方式
one way of understanding it that's sort
of a natural way to understand why it is
当它们形成晶体时，有一种稀有气体
that there's something like noble gases
when they form crystals there are
绝缘子，因为稀有气体之间的跳变基本上为零，所以这些
insulators because the hopping between
noble gases is essentially zero so these
原子轨道之间的间隔很小，但两者之间的跳跃传播
atomic orbitals they're spaced a little
bit but the hopping between that spreads
将这些轨道带入带区可以忽略不计，因此它们不会形成很宽的范围
out these orbitals into bands is
negligible so they don't form very wide
乐队，所以乐队永远不会重叠，所以这是理解它的一种方式
bands and so the bands never overlap so
um so that's one way of understanding it
但在几乎免费的模型中，几乎免费
but in a nearly free model nearly free
布里渊区边界与BZ边界之间的间隙来自
the gaps at the Brillouin zone boundary
ad BZ boundary are from from the
X的电位V的周期电位，所以如果您知道
periodic potential from potential V of X
so if you know that the periodic
潜力巨大，您应该期待两个巨大的鸿沟
potential is strong you should expect
two gaps that are pretty big opening up
在青铜的边界处，而如果电势相当弱，那么您
at the bronze own boundary whereas if
the potential is fairly weak then you
我希望可能不会在俯卧带边界上有很大的差距
expect not to have big gaps in the prone
zone boundary all right I think maybe
虽然我们还有两分钟，但我想也许我们应该停在那里
although we have two minutes left I
think maybe we should stop there and
明天我们将进一步讨论乐队理论
we'll pick up more on band theory
tomorrow
您
you